Okay בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is ק''יז Kuf Yud
Zayin בבא מציעא Bava Metzia 117, and we pick up at the
very last line of קט''ז עמוד ב', Kuf Tet Zayin Amud Bet,
בעי רבי אבא בר ממל, ba'ei Rabbi Abba bar Memel, and we
are dealing with the משנה mishna that speaks about a person renting
a second story from the person who lives on the ground floor,
and if the roof of the ground floor, the floor of the
second story, breaks through, it says that the person living on the
top has a right to come down and live in the bottom
floor until the owner fixes the roof or fixes the floor.
So let's take a look at what רבי אבא Rabbi Abba asked.
רבי אבא בר ממל Rabbi Abba bar Memel asked, top of קי''ז
עמוד א', Kuf Yud Zayin Amud Aleph, כשהוא דר לבדו הוא דר
כמעיקרא או דילמא שניהם דרין? kishu dar levado hu dar kemekara oh
dilma shneihem darin? When he says he goes down and he lives,
he has a right to live in the bottom floor, and the
גמרא gemara made it a case where it was the way it
was articulated was that the whole house was sort of משועבד, mishubad,
you know, leaned to the right of this person to be living
in the second story, and that's why he has a right to
come down and live in the first if he can't live in
the second story. So he says when he comes down and he
lives on the bottom floor, is he living כשהוא דר לבדו הוא
דר כמעיקרא, kishu dar levado hu dar kemekara, is he living with
it on his own, like he, you know, does the owner have
to leave? Because that's the way it was when he was on
the top floor, he was living all alone. או דילמא שניהם דרין,
oh dilma shneihem darin, or maybe he moves in with the owner
and they both live on the ground floor together? דאמר ליה אדעתא
דאפקינון לא אגורי לך. damar lei ada'ata de-afkinun lo aguri lakh.
Even when I sort of framed it in a way that said
that the house was משועבד mishubad to your right to live on
the second story, it never was meant to be, you know, to
the extent that I would not be able to live in my
own house. So that's an implicit reservation on the degree to which
you have rights and to which you can make demands of the
ground floor. אם תימצי לומר שניהם דרין בו, im timtza lomar shneihem
darin bo,
and if you were, you know, assume that they both would live
together, that the owner even regardless of how the contract is framed,
unless it's explicit how it's phrased, the owner would never want to
give up his right to live on the ground floor, you have
to assume that. So if you say that that's the case, כשהוא
משתמש דרך פתחים משתמש או דרך גג משתמש? kishu mishtamesh derekh petakhim
mishtamesh oh derekh gag mishtamesh? Now when the guy on the second
who, the tenant, is going to be living on the ground floor
till it gets fixed, till, you know, the second story gets fixed,
does he get to go in and out on the front door,
like any normal person would who's living on the ground floor, or
does he have to go by way of the roof, meaning does
he have to climb up the ladder to the second story the
way he normally would enter the second story, there are stairs let's
say to the second story, and then you would make a ladder
that would bring him down through the hole presumably from the second
story to the first? Okay, because, you know, maybe the guy living
in the bottom story says you have a right to live here
but I want that entrance to be just for me, you have
your own entrance. מי אמרינן דמעיקרא? mi amrinan de-mekara? Do we say
it should be like it was originally? מה מעיקרא דרך גג השתא
נמי דרך גג? ma mekara derekh gag hashta nami derekh gag? So
the same way when you lived on the second story you had
to go through the roof, you know, you had to go, take
the outside stairs, so here too it's the same. או דילמא, oh
dilma, or do we say מצי אמר ליה עליה וירידה לא קבילי
עלי? matzi amar lei aliya ve-yerida lo kibeili alai?
When I agreed to go by the second story entrance I agreed
to go up the stairs to get into my house, I didn't
agree that I have to go up the stairs, go through my
house and then downstairs again, you know, down another set of stairs.
So no, that was not, I never, you know, agreed to anything
like that and you have an obligation to provide me a place
to live, so therefore you cannot make more demands on me and
therefore I have a right to go through the front door. אם
תימצי לומר מצי אמר ליה עליה וירידה לא קבילי עלי, im timtza
lomar matzi amar lei aliya ve-yerida lo kibeili alai, and if we
assume that normally you'll see there are little letters here indicating that
how we פסקן, pasken, and normally when the גמרא gemara says if
you assume A, then what about this next case? And if you
assume that that's the case, then what about this next case? So
could be that the גמרא gemara is just saying that because it
wants to raise a lot of hypotheticals, but it's not really saying
that there's more weight on that side, it just wants to explore
another avenue. But sometimes, you know, the ראשונים rishonim and the פוסקים
poskim assume that the fact that the גמרא gemara is willing to
say let's grant that this is the case or let's assume this
is the case, what would be about the next possibility means that
we are actually פסקן paskening or it's reason to פסקן pasken that
that first assumption is the way it is. So that's why you'll
see these little letters every time the גמרא gemara does an אם
תימצי לומר. im timtza lomar. אם תימצי לומר מצי אמר ליה עליה
וירידה לא קבילי עלי, im timtza lomar matzi amar lei aliya ve-yerida
lo kibeili alai, if we assume that you can, that the tenant
can say to the owner I never agreed to go up and
down and therefore I have a right to go in the front
door, okay, שתי עליות זו אגבי זו מהו? shteialiyot zo gabi zu
mahu?
Let's say that there is a second story and a third story.
Now we're going to have to explain the scenario, which one broke,
which floor broke. שתי עליות זו אגבי זו מהו? shteialiyot zo gabi
zu mahu? אי פחתה עליונה נחית ודייר בתחתונה. if pahsa eliyona neichis
ve-dayer be-takhtona. If the third story, you know, the floor
broke through, the second of the additional stories. Anyway, if the third
story the floor broke through, then he can go ahead and live
in the bottom story. So, presumably this would be a case of
that the whole house is משועבד, meshu'abad, it's again framed in ways
to people that are living in those various, you know, second and
third stories. So he would have a right to come down and
live in the second
story, איפכא ifcha assuming let's say nobody is living in the second
story, you know, the owner wouldn't have a right to force the
tenant in the second story to accept another person living with him.
איפכא תחתונה מהו לסלקו לגמרי בעליונה. Ifcha tachtonah mahu lesalko legamrei be'elyonah.
But
let's say the second story broke through, can the owner now say
to him, you know what, move up to the third story. Don't
move down here with me, move up to the third story. מי
אמרינן דאמרינן ליה שם עליה קבלת עלך. Mi amrinan de'amrinan leih shem
aliyah kabbelt alach.
Does the owner have a right to say, look, you don't have
to go up and down, but, you know, you did agree that
you would have to go up a flight of stairs to get
into your house. So now you'll have to go up two flights
of stairs, but it's not really substantively different, okay, so therefore I'm
going to put you in the third story.
או דילמא, O dilma, or do we say, חד עליה קביל עלך
שתי עליות לא קביל עלך. Chad aliyah kabbil alach shtei aliyot lo
kabbil alach. No, he agreed to go up one flight of stairs
to get to his apartment, not two flights of stairs, so if
the second apartment breaks through you cannot put him on the third
floor. If he wants to, he can come down and live with
you on the first floor. And the גמרא Gemara says תיקו, teiku,
so we do not know the answer to those questions. Okay, now,
רבי יוסי אומר התחתון נותן את התקרה. Rabbi Yosi omer hatachton noten
et hatikrah. So רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosi says that the bottom person is the one who,
you know, the owner provides the actual like beams of the roof,
but it's the person living on the top floor that has to
provide the plaster as opposed to the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma that
says that it's the owner that provides the entire replacing of it,
you know, that's always of the floor. You know, that's always a
question when you're renting an apartment, you know, from the wall in
is the responsibility of the landlord, from the wall out is your
responsibility. And we'll see in a minute we'll deal with the case
about if the upstairs neighbor is leaking into you, is it that
they have to pay to fix the floor, you have to pay
to fix the roof. So these are standard landlord and tenant discussions.
And while the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says that the owner, the
landlord has to fix the entire floor, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says
no, the owner just provides the beams or whatever the construction material,
but the person on the top has to plaster it over. So
מאי תקרה, mai tikrah, what constitutes that building material for the roof/floor?
So רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא אמר קנים וסנואים וסיטני, Rabbi Yosi Berabbi
Chanina amar kanim vesano'im vesitni, which are like, you know, mats and
wood beams.
אמר ריש לקיש לווחין. Amar Reish Lakish levachin. And ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish says no we're talking about like wood planks. ולא פליגי, Velo
peligi, they don't argue, מר כי אתריה ומר כי אתריה, mar ki
atreih umar ki atreih, each one is according to the standards of
their place. Okay. הנהו בי תרי דהוו דיירי. Hanehu bei terei dehavu
dayerei. Now there were two people living, חד עילאי וחד תתאי, chad
ilai vechad tatai, one on the top, one on the bottom, just
like our משנה. Mishnah. איפחית מעזיבה. Ifchit ma'azivah.
Okay, and the, and you know,
the plaster of the, you know, on the floor that was of
the top and the roof of the bottom, the plaster like cracked
open, broke open. כי משי ידיה עילאי אזלי מיא ומזקי לתתאי. Ki
mashi yadeih ilai azli maya umazki letatai. And when the top person
would wash his hands, you know, turn on the water, it would
come on and it would drip on the floor and it would
drip through because the plaster is cracked and it would drip through
the roof of the bottom guy. Happens not infrequently. So רבי חייא
בר אבא אמר עליון מתקן, Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar elyon metakken,
it's the responsibility of the person living on the top floor. ורבי
אילעא משמיה דרבי חייא ברבי יוסי אמר תחתון מתקן. Verabbi Ila'i mishmei
deRabbi Chiya Berabbi Yosi amar tachton metakken. It is no, it's the
guy living on the
bottom. Okay, so let's take a look. וסימנא, Vesimana, and the way
to remember this is, ויוסף הורד מצרימה. Veyosef hurad mitzraimah. Why ויוסף
הורד מצרימה? Veyosef hurad mitzraimah? Because it's רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya בשם
beshem רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, so that sounds like יוסף, Yosef, and
הורד hurad is going down and רש"י Rashi actually says it's like
נחית, nachit, so that's תחתון, tachton, so רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi is
the one who says that it's the guy on the bottom
who has to fix it. Okay, so let's take a look.
Now, רש"י Rashi says by the way that it's important that this
is not the case of a owner and a tenant, of a
landlord and a tenant like our משנה, Mishnah, it's a case of
actually two separate owners, you know, one person owns the top floor,
one person owns the bottom. Okay, whether that would make a difference
or not, רש"י Rashi will talk about that we'll see later but
רש"י Rashi makes a point about pointing that out, maybe because if
it was a tenant and a landlord it would very clearly automatically
be the case of our משנה, Mishnah, right? And the question is
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says that the person on the top does
the plastering and the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says a person on
the bottom. So, so the גמרא Gemara is going to compare it
to our משנה, Mishnah, but so that it's not immediately a case
of our משנה, Mishnah, רש"י Rashi says it's a little different, it's
a case of separate owners. Okay, so now we're going to try
to understand what this debate is about.
לימא רבי חייא בר אבא ורבי אילעא בפלוגתא דרבי יוסי ורבנן קמיפלגי.
Leima Rabbi Chiya bar Abba veRabbi Ila'i biplugeta deRabbi Yosi verabbanan kamiflegi.
So maybe this is... paralleling the debate of רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosei
and the Rabbis exactly in our משנה, Mishnah, okay, but it's paralleling
because again as רש״י Rashi says it's not the exact same case.
So
למאן דאמר עליון מתקן Leman d'amar elyon metaken קסבר על המזיק להרחיק
את עצמו מן הניזק. kasavar al hamazik leharcheek et atzmo min hanizak.
And now we're going to conceptualize the debate of רבי יוסי Rebbi
Yosei and the Rabbis. Okay, we're going to assume that the reason
the issue about putting on the plaster is if I went ahead
and I put on let's go back to the case of the
משנה. Mishnah. I'm the landlord, I am required to make the floor,
to fix the floor, I put on the beams. You now have
a legitimate floor. I've done my job. What is the issue? The
issue is that it's not waterproof. So it might go ahead and
damage me. So that maybe is your responsibility that you're living on
the second floor to prevent your water from damaging me. Or no,
is that still included in my responsibility to take care and protect
myself that I'm not damaged? So that is a classic בבא בתרא
Bava Batra discussion. If you're doing something in your domain and I'm
doing something in my domain, you're having a barbecue and the smoke
from your barbecue is coming in and it's, you know, and it's
getting and it's providing smoke pollution in my yard or doing other
things, you know, that's harming me, who has the responsibility to move?
Me or you? That's the debate. So maybe that is exactly what
is going on in our משנה. Mishnah. Let's take a look. למאן
דאמר עליון מתקן, Leman d'amar elyon metaken, according to רבי יוסי Rebbi
Yosei that says the tenant on the second floor has to provide
the plaster, קסבר על המזיק להרחיק את עצמו kasavar al hamazik leharcheek
et atzmo מן הניזק. min hanizak. That is the מזיק hamazik because
the guy on the top floor, his water is going down and
hurting the guy on the bottom floor, so he is the one
doing the damage. The one doing the damage has to prevent the
damage from happening, so he has to provide the plaster. מן הניזק,
min hanizak, he has to distance himself from the one being damaged.
So therefore the top guy, if all the plaster is doing is
preventing water damage, that's the top guy's responsibility. ומאן דאמר תחתון מתקן,
Uman d'amar tachton metaken, and the one that says that it's the
owner and the guy on the bottom that has to provide the
plaster, קסבר על הניזק להרחיק את עצמו מן המזיק. kasavar al hanizak
leharcheek et atzmo min hamazik. No, as long if the guy is
if that guy is washing his hands in his own domain, he's
not and things are just happening indirectly, it's my responsibility if I
don't want to get damaged to move or to prevent it. And
maybe that is the debate in the משנה Mishnah between whether the
top guy provides the plaster or the bottom, and that maybe is
exactly this debate here in our case, which is almost the exact
same, except that רש״י Rashi says it's about a two separate owners
rather than a renter and an owner. So now the גמרא Gemara
saying, one minute, ותסבורא, v'tisbora, does that really make sense?
רבי יוסי ורבנן בענין נזיקין פליגי? Rebbi Yosei v'Rabanan b'inyan nezekin peligi?
That their fundamental debate in our משנה, Mishnah, רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosei
and the Rabbis is about this question of damager and damagee and
who has to distance themselves when each one is operating in their
own domain? ואיפכא שמענא להו, Ve'ipcha shemanan lehu, but we know that
they hold the reverse position. דתנן, Detnan, that we taught in a
משנה Mishnah coming up in בבא בתרא: Bava Batra: מרחיקין את האילן
מן הבור עשרים וחמש אמה. marchikin et ha'ilan min habor esrim vechamish
amot. Okay,
that you distance a, you know, your you can't have a tree
planted near a cistern or well because the roots are going to
go in and destroy and destroy the well and destroy the cistern.
So you have to keep it distance and how distance do you
have to keep it? עשרים וחמש אמה, esrim vechamish amot, which is
like twenty-five אמה, amot, which is like 30, which is like what
is that like 36 feet? Okay, so a yard about? No, 10
yards?
I'm sorry.
Okay. Right.
12 yards that is, my math is off today. Okay, anyway,
okay, so מרחיקין את האילן מן הבור עשרים וחמש אמה. marchikin et
ha'ilan min habor esrim vechamish amot. ובחרוב ובשקמה, Uvecharuv uv'shikma, and if
you're dealing with a carob tree or a שקמה, shikma, which is
a sycomore tree, ובחרוב ובשקמה, uvecharuv uv'shikma,
so חמשים אמה, hamishim ama, 50 אמה amot because there the roots
go much further distance. בין מלמעלה בין מן הצד, Ben milmala ben
min hatzad, whether it is above, even if the tree is in
a valley and the pit is on like a mount is on
the you know in a mountain, it doesn't matter because the roots
will go underneath the floor of the pit, of the of the
cistern, and will weaken the floor of the cistern. So even if
they're not level and certainly if it's מן הצד, min hatzad, if
it's just parallel you know it's off to the side if they're
on the level ground. אם הבור קודם קוצץ ונותן דמים. Im habor
kodem kotzetz venotein damim.
If
let's say the well came first, then the person planting the tree,
he shouldn't have planted that tree, and therefore the person owning the
well can demand that he cut it down or cuts it down
for him, but he does have to compensate him. Why does he
compensate him? Because at the end of the day, you know, this
guy was planting in his own domain, you know, and it was
a very later type of a thing that eventually the roots grow
and they can threaten and they can damage. So even though he
has the right to say you've got to, you know, it's your
responsibility you know because of the tree you put it second, you
have to cut it down, nevertheless he has to pay the person
who is demanding it, the owner of the cistern has to pay
for it, קוצץ ונותן דמים. kotzetz venotein damim. ואם האילן קודם לא
יקוץ, Ve'im ha'ilan kodem lo yakotz, but if the tree came first,
then you don't have to cut it down. Okay, so because then
it was your fault that you made your
well. רבי יוסי אומר אף על פי שהבור קודמת לאילן לא יקוץ.
Rabbi Yosse omer af al pi shehabeir qodemes lailan lo yaqotz.
Even though the well came first and I did something wrong, as
you know, or whatever, irresponsible by planting my tree near your well,
you cannot demand that I cut down my tree, שזה חופר בתוך
שלו וזה נוטע בתוך שלו. sheze chofer betoch shelo veze notea betoch
shelo. Your digging in your yard, I'm planting in my yard. The
fact that indirectly what I'm doing in my yard might come damage
you, that's not my responsibility, that's your responsibility. Okay, so here you
have exactly that debate. I'm operating my yard, planting my tree when
you already have this well, and according to the תנא קמא, Tanna
Kamma, I have to be the one that suffers. I did something
wrong so I have to get my tree out of there. Maybe
you compensate me, but it's my responsibility as the one that is
causing damage, על המזיק להרחיק את
עצמו. al hamaziq leharcheq et atzmo. And Rabbi Yosse says no, you're
fine. You went ahead and you did your own thing in your
own yard. You don't have to worry about that. That's not your
responsibility. If I don't want a damage, you know, I have to
go ahead and protect myself and I have to move, על הניזק
להרחיק את עצמו. al hanizaq leharcheq et atzmo. So if that's clear
and that's Rabbi Yosse, then Rabbi Yosse's idea in our משנה Mishnah
that the guy in the top has to provide the plaster has
nothing to do with על המזיק להרחיק את עצמו al hamaziq leharcheq
et atzmo because Rabbi Yosse says that it's the ניזק nizaq that
has to distance, not the מזיק. maziq. So that would point to
the owner doing the plaster. So what's going on in our משנה?
Mishnah? So אמר רבי יוסי סבר על הניזק להרחיק את עצמו. amar
Rabbi Yosse savar al hanizaq leharcheq et atzmo. You
see Rabbi Yosse holds that as long as you're operating in your
own domain,
the one who is going to get damaged, it's his responsibility to
protect himself. So that can't be what's going on in our משנה
Mishnah why he says the guy on the top has to provide
the plaster. ורבנן סברי על המזיק להרחיק את עצמו. verabbanan savrei al
hamaziq leharcheq et atzmo. And the Rabbis, and assuming it's the same
Rabbis, say the opposite. It's the one who is who's causing the
damage that has to do something. So how do you explain in
our משנה Mishnah why it seems to be reversed? אלא איכא למימר
פליגי בפלוגתא דרבי יוסי ורבנן דהתם קמיפלגי. ela ika lemeimar pligi biplugeta
deRabbi Yosse verabbanan dehatam qamiflegi.
So if you therefore say, so that that it's the debate of,
what do you call it, of two owners, a top and a
bottom, and the plaster cracked and there's water damage. Okay, that is,
you were correct in conceptualizing that as a debate. That debate of
the אמוראים Amoraim of who was it, רבי חייא בר אבא Rabbi
Chiyya bar Abba and רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosse. You are correct that
that debate of who has to provide the plaster when there's water
damage and the roof is leaking, that is the debate of רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosse and the רבנן Rabbanan in בבא בתרא. Bava Batra.
That is the debate of על המזיק להרחיק al hamaziq leharcheq or
על הניזק להרחיק את עצמו. al hanizaq leharcheq et atzmo. If it's
על המזיק להרחיק, al hamaziq leharcheq, the guy on the top floor
has to provide the plaster. If it's על הניזק להרחיק al hanizaq
leharcheq and you don't want your roof dripping in, you have to
go ahead on the bottom floor, you have to provide the plaster.
That is what's going on. And you exactly conceptualized it correctly, but
it was a different רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosse and a רבנן. Rabbanan.
It was the רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosse and the רבנן Rabbanan of
בבא בתרא. Bava Batra. That's the debate of two separate owners, who
has to plaster when it's leaking through from one to the next.
Okay, what's going on in our
משנה? Mishnah? ורבי יוסי ורבנן דהכא במאי קמיפלגי? veRabbi Yosse verabbanan dehacka
bemai qamiflegi? What are Rabbi Yosse and the Rabbis here
debating?
בחוזק תקרה קמיפלגי. bechozeq tiqra qamiflegi. But the question about the strength
of the roof. רבנן סברי מעזיבה אחזוקי תקרה הוא ואחזוקי תקרה על
התחתון רמי. rabbanan savrei maaziva achzuqei tiqra hu veachzuqei tiqra al hatachton
remei. The Rabbis held that look, when you put the plaster, that's
just making for a stronger roof and a stronger floor. It's true
you have planks, but those planks will be wobbly. You have not
done your job as making the roof, rebuilding the roof. You as
the owner have not done your job without the plaster. It's not
enough that okay, look, he can walk on the planks. No, part
of a solid roof and a solid floor is the plaster. And
that's why if you're the owner and you have to, you know,
provide the, you know, fix the problem, you have to do it
with the plaster. רבי יוסי סבר מעזיבה אשויי גומות הוא ואשויי גומות
אעליון רמי. Rabbi Yosse savar maaziva ashvei gumot hu veashvei gumot aeilyon
remei. No,
the plaster there is really just, you know, the roof is solid
enough and the floor is solid enough. You have to imagine a
case that it is. I don't know, maybe it's knocked in with
nails or something. Anyway, and therefore the reason that we plastered over,
it's only so that you have a nice smooth floor. It is
not really to provide the strong floor, but it's that it should
be nice and smooth. You know, again, it's like in the tenant-landlord
relationship. Everything from the walls on the outside is your responsibility. So
this is something that's about the living conditions in your space. It
is not about there fundamentally being a roof or floor. And therefore
it's you the tenant's responsibility, not the landlord's responsibility. Okay, ואחזוקי תקרה
על התחתון רמי. veachzuqei tiqra al hatachton remei. Now is that really
true? ואמר רב אשי כי הוינא בי רב כהנא הוי אמרינן מודה
רבי יוסי בגירי דיליה. veamar Rav Ashi ki havina bei Rav Kahana
havay amrinan modeh Rabbi Yosse begirei dileih.
So one minute. Now the גמרא Gemara is going back and saying
one minute, one minute. You said that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosse says
על הניזק להרחיק את עצמו, al hanizaq leharcheq et atzmo, right?
So in that case that על הניזק להרחיק את עצמו, al hanizaq
leharcheq et atzmo, and therefore the guy on the top does not
have to worry if there's water damage below. But... going back, you
know, to the רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi and the רבנן Rabbanan in
בבא בתרא, Bava Batra, forget our משנה Mishna for a minute. And
but okay, נחזי nachzei just of simple water damage and so on,
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi holds that על הניזק להרחיק את עצמו. al
ha-nizak le-harchik et atzmo. But one minute, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi agrees
when it’s your own arrows, גירי דיליה, girei dilei,
meaning, if it is normally the case where you could say hey,
if you want to protect yourself you should be the one to
move because I do something not only in my domain, but actually
I do it and then I walk away and then it happens
over a period of time later. Okay, I plant the tree and
eventually the roots grow. Okay, that’s not my action. What I did
at the time was okay, later the roots grow, that’s your responsibility
to move away from it. That’s where רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi could
say על הניזק להרחיק את עצמו. al ha-nizak le-harchik et atzmo. But
if I’m doing stuff in my in my property that is directly
through my action going into your property and damaging you, let’s like
a בבא קמא Bava Kamma case, I’m chopping wood and the splinters
are flying into your property and hitting you, then obviously that’s אדם
המזיק adam ha-mazik and that’s על המזיק להרחיק את עצמו. al ha-mazik
le-harchik et atzmo. I have the responsibility. That’s גירי דיליה, girei dilei,
my arrows. So the גמרא'ס Gemara's saying this water case is my
arrows because this water case I’m spilling the water and it’s going
through the through you know through the what do you call plaster
and going and hitting you below. That’s exactly a case that even
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi would agree. So how could we say going
back, forgetting our משנה, Mishna, in the debate of you know the
plaster and the water dripping that that’s the debate of רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosi and the רבנן? Rabbanan? So the גמרא Gemara says no,
דפסיקי מיא והדר נפלי, de-psiki maya ve-hadar naflei, it's a case where
first the water hits and then slowly it you know drips down
like sometimes that happens over time, right? It slowly absorbs, absorbs, absorbs
into the roof and then finally it starts leaking, you know, into
the bottom apartment. So in that case it would be a case
not nearly as time-lapsed as the tree, but it would not be
a direct case of אדם המזיק. adam ha-mazik. Okay, so that’s what
the debate is in בבא בתרא Bava Batra and the plastering case,
but the debate in our משנה Mishna has nothing to do with
plaster and water damage. We’re not even talking about water damage. Water
damage we would assess differently maybe, maybe that’s a בבא בתרא Bava
Batra case, you know, but that’s a case and this is why
רש"י Rashi distinguished it, that’s a case of not two owners and
damage, מזיק mazik and ניזק, nizak, that’s a case of the responsibility
of the landlord to the tenant. And the question is whose responsibility
is the plaster on. Okay great, let's take a look at the
next משנה. Mishna. הבית
והעלייה של שנים שנפלו. Ha-bayit ve-ha-aliya shel shenayim she-naflu. Okay, so now
you have again the case of the ground floor and the top,
but this is a case where it’s not landlord and tenant, it’s
של שנים, shel shenayim, two separate owners and the house fell down.
So אמר בעל העלייה לבעל הבית לבנות. amar ba’al ha-aliya le-ba’al ha-bayit
livnot. So the guy who owns the second floor says to the
guy who owns the ground floor, could you please build up your
ground floor so I can then build my second floor on top
of it. ואינו רוצה לבנות ve-eino rotzeh livnot and he doesn’t want
to, he’s got other places to live, he’s he’s short on cash.
So what options does the second-story guy have? So הרי בעל העלייה
בונה את הבית ודר בתוכה, harei ba’al ha-aliya boneh et ha-bayit ve-dar
betocha, so the guy who used to be living on the second
story goes ahead and builds the house עד שיתן לו את יציאותיו
ad she-yiten lo et yetziotav until the until the owner, the person
who has the rights to the bottom story, pays him for his
labor, you know, basically pays him for his expenses, and expenses includes
the effort and the labor and all of that. So I, if
I lived on the top floor floor, I can go ahead and
I don’t have to physically build it myself, I can lay out
the cash, hire a firm to go ahead and build it. They
go ahead and build and build the ground floor and I will
now live in the ground floor until you pay me what I
paid the firm, and once you pay me what I paid the
firm then I will go ahead and build my second story. You
don’t have to pay me how much the property improved. I might
actually have been giving you a gift, you know, I paid the
firm a hundred thousand dollars, the property is now worth a hundred
and fifty thousand, but you do have to pay me the money
I outlaid and then I will go ahead and build the second
story. And that presumably is because I have a right to be
living on this property and if you’re not doing your part, this
is how we’re going to make it work. Okay, רבי יהודה אומר
אף זה דר בתוך של חבירו צריך להעלות לו שכר. Rabbi Yehuda
omer af zeh dar be-toch shel chaveiro tzarich le-ha'alot lo sachar. No,
this is a case of that somebody is you’re still living in
this other guy’s house. Yes I went ahead and I paid paid
the contractor and they built the house, but but you, I don't
own this house, you know, you have the rights to a house
down here. So effectively, and if we say you know, you have
rights you know, you own the property or you have rights to
the property to allow you to build the house. So effectively what
I’ve done is I’ve built a house in your property, you know,
it might be partially mine too but it’s your but it’s your
property but you have the rights to the house that’s built here.
So I built a house for you. Okay, you have to pay
me back, but I built the house for you. So if that’s
true, it’s your house, I can’t live in it without paying you
rent. That’s a principle about you know זה נהנה וזה חסר, zeh
neheneh ve-zeh chaseir, זה נהנה וזה לא חסר, zeh neheneh ve-zeh lo
chaseir, we’ll get to that in the גמרא, Gemara, but basically I’m
living in your house without paying you rent, that’s not good, if
I were to do that I would have to pay you rent.
So אלא בעל העלייה בונה את הבית ואת העלייה. ela ba'al ha-aliya
boneh et ha-bayit ve-et ha-aliya. So what I can do though is
I can pay the the you know contractors to build the whole
thing, the ground floor and the second floor. מקרס העליון mekares ha'elyon
and
I go ahead and all the way to the top and I
put the roof on the top floor. ויושב, veyoshev, now there's a
question if the גירסא girsa says ויושב בה veyoshev ba or ויושב
בבית. veyoshev babayit. תוספות Tosafot prefers the גירסא girsa ויושב בה veyoshev
ba עד שיתן לו יציאותיו. ad sheyitten lo yetzi'osav.
And I go ahead and I live in the second story, I
don't let you live on the ground floor. You know, you have
no right to live in the ground floor. I paid the money,
I can keep you out, okay? But so once you pay me
for my expenditures on the ground floor, then you can go ahead
and live in it, but I am only but I do not
have a right to live there. That essentially is yours that I
paid for and that I have rights to and I can keep
you out of, okay, until you pay me back. But it's still
yours and I can only live on the second story. And רש״י
Rashi says that it's I could live on once I have the
ability to live in the second story, I could also live in
the first story because it would be a case of זה נהנה.
zeh neheneh. I'm not getting any benefit, right? Since I could just
as easily live in the second story, I'm living in the first.
I don't have to pay you for it because it's not a
case of זה נהנה וזה חסר zeh neheneh vezeh choser or זה
נהנה וזה לא חסר. zeh neheneh vezeh lo choser. I'm not getting
anything from you because I could just as easily live in the
second story. תוספות Tosafot questions that based on the earlier גמרא, Gemara,
which is no, if you were living in the second story, you
would have to go up the the stairs on the outside, so
you actually have a benefit from living in the first story. Okay,
that's the issue. But we get the basic idea. אמר רבי יוחנן,
amar Rabbi Yochanan, בשלושה מקומות bishlosha mekomos שנה לנו רבי יהודה, shana
lanu Rabbi Yehuda, אסור לאדם שיהנה מממון חברו. assur leadam sheyehene mimmamon
chaveiro. Okay, there were three places that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda teaches
us that you're not allowed to benefit from your friend's money. Now,
you know, obviously you're not allowed to do it, you know, take
stuff that doesn't isn't yours. But what this means is is that
even though there would be a reason to say that you would
not have to pay back because like he's not losing anything from
it and and we'll see the cases. Nevertheless, because of this the
way sort of רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot seem to frame this,
you know, might be more of an ethical idea here. It's improper
to be benefiting from somebody without their, you know, willingly giving it
to you and therefore we had to פסקן pasken a הלכה halacha
that would prevent this from happening. So we can see if this
is a halachic principle or an ethical principle, but there are three
places where it would seem like you wouldn't have to pay and
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda still insists that you have to pay because
we don't you're not should not benefit from your friend's property without
their acquiescence. חדא הך דתנן, chada hach detnan, the first is our
משנה mishna that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that no, you can't
live in the house even if you built the house, it still
now belongs to the the owner of the bottom floor and you
can't live in it unless you wanted to pay him rent and
therefore you have to build a second story as well. So even
though it's a case of זה נהנה zeh neheneh and let's assume
it's this is a whole בבא קמא Bava Kamma discussion. Is it
זה חסר zeh choser or זה לא חסר? zeh lo choser? Does
the guy on the ground floor lose out or not? We'll get
to that in the גמרא, Gemara, but right now we're assuming that
the guy on the ground floor doesn't even lose anything. You built
it, you live in it, he's losing nothing. And even though he's
losing nothing, you're benefiting from his property, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda doesn't
want it and therefore he forces you to build the second story.
אידך מאי היא, idach mai hi, what's the other one? דתנן, detnan,
we taught in the משנה, mishna, הנותן צמר לצבע לצבוע לו אדום
וצבעו שחור. hanosein tzemar letzeva litzbo'a lo adom vetzeva'o shachor. You gave
wool to a dyer in order to dye it red and he
accidentally dyed it black. שחור וצבעו אדום, shachor vetzeva'o adom, or black
and he dyed it red. רבי מאיר אומר, Rabbi Meir omer, נותן
לו דמי צמרו. nosein lo d'mei tzemaro. You basically just, okay, so
you the dyer, you did something wrong and you did a שינוי
shinuy and שינוי קונה shinuy koneh and that makes it, you know,
because you've changed it not with his acquiescence and so on. Now
you own the wool, you pay him for the wool and you're
done. Okay, you shouldn't have done it, but he gets his money
back for his wool and now it's yours. You break it, you
buy it, okay. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, but רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says no. אם השבח יתירה על ההוצאה נותן לו את
ההוצאה ואם ההוצאה יתירה על השבח נותן לו את השבח. im hashevach
yeseira al hahotza'a nosein lo es hahotza'a ve'im hahotza'a yeseira al hashevach
nosein lo es hashevach. That if it
the it's worth now more than it was when it was undyed
wool, so if the improvement, the שבח, shevach, the, you know, it's
greater market value
is greater than the expenses, you know, the the the dyes and
the labor etc. of the person who did it, then the owner
just pays for the expenses, the guy his expenses, and he walks
away with this improved wool and he benefits, you know, he profits
the difference. However, if the guy the expenses exceeded the the improvement,
then he just goes ahead and the owner just pays him for
the higher value of the wool and he doesn't pay him for
all of his expenses. So he's not he doesn't gain anything, but
he's not out anything. All right. So so what does that have
to do with anything? So because the way at least רש״י Rashi
explains it is,
if
we would say you just keep you the dyer just keep the
wool, so, you know, you had somebody bring you wool and now
you've made a whole nice, you know, beautiful, you know, you know,
fine wool and now you've dyed it and now you're just getting
that benefit. Okay, you'll pay him for his wool, but you're still
benefiting from it in that he procured it and brought it for
you and so on. Okay, it seems a little funny that that's
the dynamic that's going on, but that's what the גמרא Gemara says.
It's inappropriate, we don't like that end result that you want you
the dyer who made this mistake wind up with this wool that
was brought for you. That's being נהנה neheneh from
ממון. mamon. he has the upper hand. All right, but it's motivated
by we don't want you to just get the wool, you know,
and benefit from this exchange. Okay, so
ואידך מאי, v'idach mai, what's the third? It now we תנן במתניתין,
tenan be'matnitin, מי שפרע מקצת חובו mi shepara miktzat chovo והשליש את
שטרו. ve'hishlish et shtaro. So ראובן Reuven owes שמעון Shimon $100 and
he's paid him up 25. And now שמעון Shimon is putting a
lot of pressure on him to pay up the rest. So ראובן
Reuven says, look, we'll give this שטר shtar over to לוי, Levy,
right, because שמעון Shimon holds the שטר shtar that says that, you
know, ראובן Reuven owes me $100. So ראובן Reuven paid the 25.
Now, how does he get that? Well, maybe he gets a receipt.
Okay, but here's what they do instead of a receipt because שמעון
Shimon says I really want the rest of the money. So ראובן
Reuven says, fine, here's what we're going to do. Don't write me
a receipt, give the שטר shtar to לוי, Levy, ואמר לו, ve'amar
lo, and he says to him, אם אני נותן לך מכאן ועד
זמן פלוני, im ani noten lecha mikan ve'ad zman ploni, if I
pay you up the rest of the debt, the other $75, by
next Monday, תן לו שטרו, ten lo shtaro, okay, then ואם איני,
ve'im eini, excuse me, ואם איני נותן לך מכאן ועד זמן פלוני
תן לו שטרו. ve'im eini noten lecha mikan ve'ad zman ploni ten
lo shtaro.
If I don't pay you up, you know, I say to לוי,
Levy, if I don't pay שמעון Shimon up, ראובן Reuven says to
לוי, Levy, if I don't pay שמעון Shimon up by next Monday,
then give him back the שטר shtar and I'll pay the whole
$100. Okay? So he paid up 25 and שמעון Shimon wants all
his money and said, look, here's what we're going to do. לוי
Levy is going to hold on to the שטר. shtar. If I
don't get you the money by next week, don't write me a
receipt, take the שטר shtar back and he knows that 25 was
paid, but take the שטר shtar back and then I'll have to
pay you again the whole 100. All right, and we'll make the
first 25 a מתנה. matana. Somehow it's not a ריבית ribbit problem.
All right. But if I do pay you back, but if I
do get that money, then you'll know it's only $75, I'll pay
you the 75, I'll get the שטר shtar and I'll rip it
up. Okay,
so that's the condition. Now, is that condition binding? הגיע זמן ולא
נתן, higia zman velo natan, the time came and I did not
pay up. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi אומר omer יתן. yitein. Okay, רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi says you give the שטר shtar back to שמעון
Shimon and שמעון Shimon can now collect the whole $100. רבי יהודה
אומר Rabbi Yehuda omer, לא יתן. lo yitein. No,
even though that was the condition, it's not binding, it doesn't work.
And why? And now again, we're saying because רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
does not want somebody to be improperly benefiting from somebody else's property.
So again, the way תוספות Tosafot frames it is the legal principles
actually should be that all of this is okay. You were קונה
koneh the wool with שינוי. shinui. You made a condition and therefore
you should have to pay the full 100. You lived in the
house because you built the house. All of those fundamentally should be
okay. But because of this ethical principle that it's improper to, you
know, benefit from somebody's property without their acquiescence, we're going to change
the הלכה, halacha, we're going to say go ahead and give back
the wool and we'll figure and do a payment that benefits him.
Go ahead and build the second story, don't live in the first
story. And you don't have to give the שטר shtar back, pay
just what you owe. Okay, that's how the גמרא Gemara is understanding
these positions.
So the גמרא Gemara says,
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda אומר, omer okay, אמאי? amai? So the גמרא
Gemara pushes back on רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan claim. Who says this
is true? This is what's going on. דילמא, dilma, maybe each one
of these has its own legal principles. דילמא עד כאן לא קאמר
רבי יהודה הכא אלא משום דאיכא שחרוריתא, dilma ad kan lo ka'amar
Rabbi Yehuda hacha ela mishum de'ika shachrurita, that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
only says the principle in our case of the משנה Mishna that
you can't live in the bottom floor because you blacken the walls.
You live in a place, you know, and the walls get sooty
and black and so on. So it's a case of לא זה
נהנה וזה לא חסר. lo zeh neheneh vezeh lo chaser. It's a
case of זה נהנה וזה חסר. zeh neheneh vezeh chaser. Not only
are you benefiting, the owner is losing. He's going to pay you
for the construction costs of a new house and you've been living
in it for a year and you're giving him a house that's
a year worn in. So that's a case of זה נהנה וזה
חסר. zeh neheneh vezeh chaser. And therefore that's why, מעיקר הדין, me'ikar
hadin, you have to pay. When you're benefiting and the other person
is losing, you absolutely have an obligation to pay for your benefit.
אי נמי לצבוע לו אדום וצבעו שחור משום דקא משני, i nami
litzboa lo adom utzva'o shachor mishum deka meshani, and now how about
the case about the red and the black? משום דקא משני, mishum
deka meshani, it's not because, oh, we don't want you to improperly
whatever. No, there's a general principle in contract law that if you
change the agreement, then the other person has the upper hand. דתנן
כל המשנה ידו על התחתונה, detnan kol hameshaneh yado al hatachtona,
whoever changes, his hand is, he has the lower hand. So it's
not because of like, fundamentally you should get the wool and blah,
blah, blah. No, you know, it's his wool, שינוי shinui isn't קונה
koneh here, you didn't try to steal it. And in terms of
what the payment is, you are the one that changed the contract,
changed the agreement, so you have the lower hand. ומי שפרע מקצת
חובו נמי הוי אסמכתא. umi shepara miktzat chovo nami havei asmachta. And
the case where I said, you know, if I don't pay you
up in the time, then I'll owe you the whole 100 again,
that's an אסמכתא. asmachta. I'm making a promise of something and incurring
a debt which I don't really expect that I'm ever going to
have to incur. ושמעינן ליה לרבי יהודה דאמר לא קני. ushmainan leh
leRabbi Yehuda de'amar lo kani. And we know רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says אסמכתא asmachta isn't קונה. koneh. Now רש״י Rashi is pretty funny.
רש״י Rashi says ושמעינן ליה לרבי יהודה, u'shaminun lei l'Rabbi Yehuda, רש״י
Rashi says here, הכא שמעינן, hacha shaminun, הכא שמעינן. hacha shaminun.
We know Rabbi Yehuda says, meaning this הלכה halacha of Rabbi Yehuda
that you don't give back the שטר shtar is our basis, our
understanding of this Rabbi Yehuda is that אסמכתא לא קניא. asmachta lo
kanya. So it could be each one of these has its own
legal principle and not this ethical point, and now we understand that
the legal principle in our משנה mishna for Rabbi Yossi is זה
נהנה וזה חסר. ze neheneh v'ze chaser. Okay. Okay. אמר רב אחא
בר אדא משמיה דעולא התחתון בא
לשנות, Amar Rav Aha bar Adda mishme d'Ulla tachton ba l'shanos, now
we're gonna go a different point. You're rebuilding the house, bottom guy
is agreeing to rebuild it. Okay, now he wants to make a
change. בגויל שומעין לו, b'gvil shomin lo, if he wants to go
ahead and make it out of like unhewn stones, which are wider
and thicker than the like carved flattened stones, you know, concrete blocks
let's say that are the bottom that make the wall, then you
listen to him because he's making a more solid foundation, so he
has the right to do it and that's good for the guy
on the top. בגזית, b'gozis, if however he wants to change it
in the other direction, going from the גויל gvil to גזית, gozis,
from unhewn stones to hewn stones, those גזית gozis stones are they
look nicer maybe they're you know smoother, but they're not as wide
and it's a weaker foundation, if that's the direction he's going and
he doesn't have a right to impose that on the guy on
the top. The guy on the top has a right for a
strong foundation. Okay. בגויל בגזית אין שומעין לו. b'gvil b'gozis ein shomin
lo. בכפיסים שומעין לו, b'kfisim shomin lo, בלבנים אין שומעין לו. b'lveinim
ein shomin lo.
Similar כפיסים kfisim are types of bricks that would be half as
wide as a לבינה, lveina, but you would put plaster between them
so the actual total of the two half-wide bricks with the plaster
would be wider than the לבינה. lveina. So if you want to
go from a לבינה lveina standard brick to this half-two halves with
a middle which is a wider foundation and a stronger foundation, you
have a right to, but if you want to switch in the
opposite direction to the single brick, you don't have a right to
do it, you're making a weaker foundation. לסכך בארזים שומעין לו, l'sachech
b'arazim shomin lo, בשקמים אין שומעין לו. b'shikmim ein shomin lo. If
you want to use cedar, you know like the ארזי לבנון, arezei
levanon, if you want to use cedar you know as your roof
then that's a stronger roof you would do it, but if you
want to switch from sycamore to cedar you can, but from cedar
to sycamore you can't, בשקמים shikmim is not as strong. למעט בחלונות
שומעין לו, l'maet b'chalonos shomin lo, להרבות בחלונות אין שומעין לו. l'harbos
b'chalonos ein shomin lo. If you on the ground floor want to
have fewer windows than you had before, you're allowed to do that,
fewer windows make for stronger walls, stronger foundation for the guy on
top. If you want to make more windows than before, then you
don't have a right to impose that on the guy on top
because it makes for a weaker walls, weaker foundation. להגביה אין שומעין
לו, l'hagbiha ein shomin lo, if you want to give yourself taller
ceilings then you don't have a right to do that. Again, if
the guy on top agrees he can do whatever he agrees to.
But if you want to make taller ceilings, you don't have a
right to do that because if his second story starts higher, first
of all he'll have to climb more stairs and second of all
it might also mean like he you know it's not as strong
of a foundation that he's it's built on. למעט שומעין
לו. l'maet shomin lo. If you want to make your lower ceilings
and have the guy have to climb fewer stairs and you know
being built closer to the ground, then that would be good for
him and then you can do. And the reverse is going to
be for the guy on the top. Because on the guy on
the top anything that is stronger in terms of his real walls,
the height of his walls, the strength and the weight of his
ceiling, all of that puts more pressure on the guy below. So
the guy on the top can do the reverse. He can make
the stuff lighter and less strong but not stronger and heavier.
Okay, העליון שבא לשנות, elyon she-ba l'shanos, the guy on the top
wants to make it different than it used to be. בגזית שומעין
לו, b'gozis shomin lo, בגויל אין שומעין לו. b'gvil ein shomin lo.
You let him go to the hewn stones but you don't let
him go in the direction of the unhewn בגויל. b'gvil. בכפיסים אין
שומעין לו, b'kfisim ein shomin lo, בלבנים שומעין לו. b'lveinim shomin lo.
You let him, you don't let him go
to the two half bricks with the middle because that's heavier, wider,
you do let him go from that to make it smaller, the
single brick. בארזים אין שומעין לו, b'arazim ein shomin lo, בשקמים שומעין
לו. b'shikmim shomin lo. You don't let him switch his roof to
cedar, but you do let him switch it to sycamore. He can't
go to something stronger, he can go to something weaker. להרבות בחלונות
שומעין לו. l'harbos b'chalonos shomin lo. You let him have more windows
that makes his walls weaker, less heavy, puts less pressure below. למעט
בחלונות אין שומעין לו, l'maet b'chalonos ein shomin lo, fewer windows אין
שומעין לו, ein shomin lo, you don't listen to him. להגביה אין
שומעין לו, l'hagbiha ein shomin lo, to make his second story taller
you don't, puts more pressure below. למעט שומעין לו, l'maet shomin lo,
to make it smaller you do listen to him.
So it's actually interesting, wait, was that the same as the one?
Oh, so both of them have that הלכה halacha is the same.
להגביה אין שומעין לו l'hagbiha ein shomin lo and למעט שומעין לו.
l'maet shomin lo. That's actually the same for both. Okay, it's not
good for the top guy to have to go higher, so you
can't make your ground story higher, and it's not good for the
ground guy to have the top floor higher because it puts more
weight. So that's the only one that's not reversed. Also interesting that
it didn't totally be parallel there which one was the שומעין shomin
and the אין שומעין ein shomin the order. Anyway, אין לו לזה
ולא לזה מה? ein lo l'ze v'lo l'ze ma? Now... Let's say
neither of them have the ability to build up to build.
They're both not interested in building. They don't have the wherewithal. What's
the הלכה *halacha*? Now what do you want to do with it?
So רש״י *Rashi* says you want to sell the land. תוספות *Tosafos*
says no, you don't want to sell the land, you want to
plant in the land. Okay, but basically what it's asking is who
what are the land rights that the top guy has? And you'd
have to explain that this wasn't made clear before. So it was
like the two of us, ראובן ושמעון *Reuven v'Shimon* both bought the
land from לוי *Levi*, and they each chipped in a certain amount
of money and they said this is how we're going to divide
it. Or but they never spelled out who had the land rights,
I'll take the top, you take the bottom. Or they both got
it in an inheritance and they split, I'll take the top, you
take the bottom, but they never spelled out the land rights. So
now we're asking, what's the bottom line, the story with those land
rights? So תניא *Tanya* we taught in a ברייתא *Baraisa* רבי נתן
אומר תחתון נוטל שני חלקים ועליון שליש *Rebbi Noson omer tachton notel
shnei chalakim v'elyon shlish* that the guy on the bottom
is considered to have two-thirds ownership of the land and the guy
on the top one-third. וחכמים אומרים תחתון שלשה חלקים ועליון רביע *v'Chachamim
omrim tachton shlosha chalakim v'elyon revi'a*. No, the guy on the bottom
has three-quarters, the guy on the top one-quarter. I mean you would
assume that the guy on the bottom is more the person who's
closer to the land and more assumed to be the owner or
has a greater stake in it, but it's not exactly
clear why it has to be that way. So let's see how
the גמרא *Gemara* concludes. אמר רבא *Amar Rava* says Rava נקט רבי
יוחנן בידך *nakat Rebbi Yochanan beyadcha*, you should accept רבי יוחנן's *Rebbi
Yochanan's* position in your hand, meaning you should פסקן *pasken* like, actually
it says רבי נתן *Rebbi Noson*, you assume that he is the
right position. Why? דדיינא הוא ונחית לעומקא דדינא *de-dayana hu v'nachis l'umka
de-dina*. He is like a דיין *dayan* and he was the head
of a בית דין *beis din* and he really deeply understands these
monetary laws. קסבר *kasavar*
how much does the top
floor impact the bottom one? רש״י *Rashi* sort of says it's like
because you have a second story, it makes the now it's likely
that it'll shorten the life of the bottom story. The bottom story
is less stable now because it's got the weight of the top.
It'll shorten the life like a third of its lifespan. So that
shows that the guy on the top has like a third of
the rights to the entire property. I have to tell you I'm
not exactly sure how to connect those dots.
And תוספות *Tosafos* says again that we're not talking about selling, because
if it's selling you conceptualize it as I have the, you have
the rights to build the ground floor, I have the rights to
build a second floor. So if you want to sell it and
I don't want to sell it,
then you can only sell to somebody who's going to build the
ground floor, you can't sell something more than the rights you have.
Now I guess the question is if we both want to sell
it, how do we divide the money? Let's say there's mineral rights
and those types of questions. So תוספות *Tosafos* says that actually, even
though this might seem a little fair, the conclusion of the גמרא
*Gemara*, there was a natural way to assume that the guy on
the bottom because he was living on the ground floor, he owned
the property, and the guy on the top
just owns the second floor and the right to access it. So
in a way it's a חידוש *chiddush* in the גמרא *Gemara* that
since the second floor has an impact on the ground floor, that
also shows us that the second floor has certain rights to the
property, either a third or a quarter. We'll end here.